

DARWIN OTONIEL MATEOS SÁNCHEZ

Mérida, Yucatán, MX, 97305 • +52 (993) 174-1497 • ethan06@gmail.com

Skill Highlights

Team Player • Oriented detail • Complex problem solver • Innovative

Language

Spanish - Native • English

OVERVIEW

As a seasoned Software Developer with over 13 years of experience, I possess extensive knowledge of web-based, multi-threaded applications as well as front-end development using the latest web technologies. My expertise lies in developing customer service-oriented applications, making me a valuable asset to any team in need of a Senior WordPress Developer.

Throughout my career, I have worked on a range of projects using Git, Jira, Scrum methodology, Cloudflare, and custom management services. I have developed websites for various business areas, including Healthcare, Tourism, Real Estate, Non-profit, Government, and e-Commerce, utilizing WordPress and a range of related technologies such as HTML5, CSS3, SASS, jQuery, Gutenberg, React JS, Bootstrap, Material UI, and XDebug.

Additionally, I have significant experience conducting technical analysis and have provided nearshore and offshore outsourced development services. I have liaised with users to define requirements for website development, effectively translating requests into programming specifications. As a trusted technical advisor for companies, I am responsible for creating environments, load structure, and information independently.

My work ethic is process-oriented, ensuring quality coding programming, and I am self-taught in Object-Oriented Programming. I possess excellent team building skills, willing to collaborate and share knowledge to achieve the team's goals.

Software Engineer | WordPress Developer | PHP Programmer | Frontend Developer

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SENIOR WORDPRESS DEVELOPER @ ENCORA [DEC 2020 - JAN 2023]

I played a critical role in debugging, maintaining, and improving internal projects. I was responsible for staying abreast of new trends in web development and utilizing my expertise to provide solutions to complex issues based on PHP, WordPress, and JavaScript.

In addition, I successfully maintained WordPress sites, including updating plugins, implementing responsive design, and optimizing SEO tags and Analytics. I also leveraged my skills to mockup responsive web designs based on web standards, accessibility, and search engine optimization.

I demonstrated proficiency in debugging code in browsers and conducted response and cross-browsing testing. Furthermore, I was well-versed in version control using Git and deployed updates in Develop, Stage, and QA environments.

SENIOR WORDPRESS DEVELOPER @ ITCRAFTSHIP [FEB 2021 - OCT 2022]

- Debugging, maintenance and improvements for internal projects, research for new trends in web development.
- Maintenance of WordPress sites, updates plugins, responsive design, SEO tags and Analytics.
- Mockup responsive web design based on web standards, accessibility and search engine optimization.
- Solution of issues based on PHP, WordPress and JavaScript.
- Debugging code in browsers. Response and cross browsing testing.
- Version control in Git.
- Deploy updates in Develop, Stage, QA and Production environments

SENIOR WORPRESS DEVELOPER @ KSQUARE INC [APR 2018 - NOV 2020]

Debugging, maintenance and improvements for internal projects, research for new trends in web development.

- Mockup responsive web design based on web standards, accessibility and SEO.
- Solution of issues based on PHP, WordPress and JavaScript.
- Debugging code in browsers. Response and cross browsing testing.
- Coding documentation.
- Version control in Git.

SENIOR WORDPRESS DEVELOPER @ BOY SCOUTS OF AMERICA [APR 2018 – APR 2020]

Development (from scratch) and sustenance of WordPress themes and plugins following BSA guidelines on design and development, color schema, design patterns, etc.

Help desk support to solve any issue from the client side related to performance, maintenance and info management.

- Solution of issues based on PHP, WordPress and jQuery.
- Mockup responsive web design based on web standards, accessibility and SEO.
- Debugging code in browsers and XDEBUG.
- · Response and cross browsing testing.
- Coding documentation.
- Version control in Git.
- · Kanban board tracking in JIRA.
- Scrum methodology to develop each task.

SENIOR SOFTWARE SPECIALIST @ HCL TECHNOLOGIES [FEB 2017- OCT 2017]

Assigned to develop components based on React is for USAA and solve issues about performance.

- Mockup responsive web design based on web standards.
- Solution of tasks based on JavaScript (React).
- Debugging code in browsers. Code testing with Mocha.
- Code documentation with Markdown. Version control in Gitlab.
- Follow-up meetings based on the Agile methodology.

FRONTEND DEVELOPER @ JUSTIA [2015-2017]

Website development, maintenance and debugging.

- Mockup responsive web design based in best web techniques
- Identify usability and develop functional and smooth, easy-to-operate and eye-catching web applications.
- Work on open source, internal, and client projects focusing on CSS, responsive web, accessibility, and performance.

- I helped clients build out their designs while thinking about accessibility, responsiveness, and modular reusable CSS (Sass).
- Work with the team to make various client projects and products, building out CSS (Sass), HTML (Own template), and vanilla JavaScript.

SIDE PROJECTS

Definition6 - National Hypertension Control Initiative Support American Heart Association @ [JAN 2023 - March 2023]

https://nhci.heart.org/

As a WordPress developer in the National Hypertension Control Initiative Support American Heart Association project, my role would involve collaborating with a team of developers and designers to create and maintain a website that supports the initiative's objectives.

My expertise in WordPress development would be critical in developing a user-friendly website that meets the needs of the target audience, including healthcare professionals, patients, and the general public.

In addition to working closely with the design team to create a visually appealing website, I would be responsible for ensuring that the site is responsive, optimized for search engines, and integrates with various third-party tools, such as analytics and social media platforms.

Collaborating with other developers, I would also be responsible for testing the website, identifying and resolving bugs, and ensuring that it is secure and scalable.

FREELANCE @ [2014-2015]

Work with several clients to do frontend development on their projects, including HTML5, CSS3, vanilla JavaScript, and custom WordPress themes from scratch.

LEADING WEB APPLICATIONS @ FRACTALIA [2008-2014]

Head lead of Web application area, managing a team of designers and developers to rise up web projects for different kinds of clients related to government, non-profit, health, real estate business areas.

- Project management, Brainstorming, planning, design, development websites, Social media strategies. Developed and implemented effective solutions that are integrated to company's information technology standards.
- Monitored technical aspects of the front-end delivery for several projects. Worked closely with the design team and project managers and ensured projects are delivered in a timely manner.
- Converted Photoshop layouts to web pages using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, PHP and WordPress Ensured projects meet the industry standards.
- Worked on project estimation that included team members, and the development hours required Recommended technical solutions and architecture to clients.
- Interpreted and executed designs correctly as requested by clients. Perform website maintenance and enhancements.
- Write web pages using a combination of markup languages.
- Create documents and specifications for functional requirements. Develop prototypes and high-quality mock-ups.
- Provide assistance to the bank-end developers in troubleshooting and coding. Create browser and platform compatible CSS (cascading style sheets) codes. Maintain consistency in design and layout.
- Perform browser testing and debugging.
- Optimize website performance using the latest technology.

TECHNICAL

- Basic creative design skills in Layout and Graphics using:
 - o Adobe Photoshop
 - o Zeplin
 - o Figma
 - o Illustrator.
 - o Website and apps mockups, mind maps.
- Web Skills:
 - o CSS3, SASS
 - o HTML5
 - o PHP
 - o WordPress
 - o SEO, SEM, web standards and accessibility
 - o Cross-browser compatibility
 - JavaScript, jQuery,
 - o Mobile web designs
 - o Git (Github Gitlab)
 - o NPM, Grunt, Gulp.
- Operating Systems: Windows, Linux, Macintosh.

OTHER SKILLS

- Project management. Brainstorming.
- Planning, design and development websites.
- Knowledge of Social Media strategies
- Some experience teaching. Good interpersonal skills.
- Strong communication and research skills.

QUALIFICATIONS

- Online Marketing Fundamentals by Google. 2017
- Redes Sociales para Negocios Seminary. 2013
- SEO posicionamiento en Google seminary. 2013
- HTML5 course. 2011
- Multimedia development course. 2007

EDUCATION

BACHELOR, ADMINISTRATIVE COMPUTING, 2007

Universidad Juárez Autónoma de Tabasco, Villahermosa, Tabasco, MX